Guide to the Heart of Brooklyn records CBHM.0024
Center for Brooklyn History
Heart of Brooklyn records
1997-2023
Center for Brooklyn History
McClean, Denise
CBHM.0024
1.6 Linear feet in 4 manuscript boxes, 127,765 digital files (380 GB) on 1 portable hard drive
Heart of Brooklyn was a non-profit cultural consortium that included Brooklyn Children's Museum, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Public Library, Prospect Park Alliance, and Prospect Park Zoo. Records document the organization's activities from 1997 to their official closure in 2023. Items include founding documents, surveys and reports, materials concerning various programs and tourism initiatives, financial records, promotional materials, and closing documents.
Conditions Governing Access
Some digital files are restricted due to personal identifying information. See sub-series 1.4 for a full description. Other materials open to researchers without restriction.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The hard drive in this collection is not available to researchers, file access will be provided on alternative hardware.
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Denise McClean, 2023.
Arrangement
Series 1: Administrative Records is arranged in four sub-series by subject, with the exception of sub-series 1.4, which is separated by format. Folders are arranged in loose chronological order.
Series 2: Surveys and Reports is arranged in chronological order with the exception of the items in box 3 folder 7.
Series 3: Programs is arranged chronologically.
Series 4: Promotion is arranged chronologically.
See sub-series 1.4 for arrangement of digital records.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Art Association records (ARC.012)
Brooklyn Ephemera Collection, Prospect Park Alliance (BCMS.0007)
Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences publications and ephemera (ARC.138)
Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences records (ARC.011)
Brooklyn Public Library publications (ARC.161)
Historical Note
The Brooklyn Children's Museum, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Public Library, Prospect Park Alliance, and Prospect Park Zoo spent years managing an informal relationship through cross-institutional programs and events. In 1997, these institutions began to explore the creation of an independent non-profit, initially called the Brooklyn Cultural Consortium, to promote the member institutions as local and regional cultural heritage destinations, coordinate multi-institutional programs, complete a comprehensive visitor survey, and establish road markers and signage.
In early 2001 the consortium hired a part-time consultant and was awarded a planning grant from the Wallace Foundation. The consortium was named Heart of Brooklyn (HOB) and began conducting focus groups, committee meetings, and community outreach. HOB was formally incorporated in June 2001 and launched on February 13, 2002, with a celebration at Grand Army Plaza. In the Spring, HOB launched its member calendar, which served as a reference guide to highlight activities at HOB institutions and began overseeing the Brooklyn Cultural Adventures Program (BCAP). BCAP quickly became a HOB signature program, offering summer camp sessions with a focus on programs at member institutions. The HOB website was launched in December.
In 2003, HOB began hosting Neighborhood Weekends, a celebration featuring programming from HOB member institutions. The first was held at the Ebbets Field Houses, attracting 150 participants, and the second at the Red Hook Houses, which saw an attendance of 600. Later that year HOB hired an economic development consultant to analyze potential commercial revitalization in Central Brooklyn. That research led to the creation of Crown Heights Renaissance, a program to promote and strengthen the commercial corridors surrounding member communities. HOB also launched their e-newsletter Heartbeats, and BKLYN Magazine, a quarterly publication highlighting Brooklyn people and businesses that was transferred to Townhouse Communications the following year.
HOB staff moved into their first dedicated office space in February 2005, a storefront at 789 Washington Avenue. Staff members began attending trade shows, partnering with other tourism initiatives, and launched Experience the Heart of Brooklyn, a program that targeted visitors through themed packages and itineraries to increase tourism to member institutions and Central Brooklyn. The HOB Trolley, launched in 2001 to shuttle visitors between member institutions expanded to assist residents underserved by the MTA and tourists from Manhattan to cultural and shopping destinations in Central Brooklyn.
By 2011, HOB had enrolled 4,000 children in BCAP, created 50,000 cross marketing brochures, provided 100,000 free trolley rides, and conducted 50 focus groups with 8,000 individuals surveyed. However, in 2013 funding challenges forced HOB to close their storefront office, terminate staff positions, and discontinue several programs. HOB never financially recovered and in 2015 the website was taken down as the process to dissolve the 501 (c)3 began. After a delay due to the Covid-19, HOB was officially closed in early 2023.
Scope and Contents
The Heart of Brooklyn records document the organization's activities from 1997 to their official closure in 2023. The bulk of this collection is born digital or digitized material, held on a hard drive and copied to the Center for Brooklyn History's server. See sub-series 1.4 for a full description.
Printed material includes early documents created before incorporation, including an exploratory report and business plan. Founding documents include paperwork filed to register Heart of Brooklyn as a 501(3)(c), charities registration, name registration, and SS-4 applications. Surveys and reports include data collected from member institution visitors and organizational assessments, achievements, and challenges.
Program materials include a draft plan and report to secure continued funding for Crown Heights Renaissance. The report outlines financial information, promotional examples, and letters of support. Experience the Heart of Brooklyn materials include brochures, clippings, calendars, and itineraries.
Nonprofit organizations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Advertising -- Tourism; Tourism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Reports; New York (State) -- Surveys; Brochures; Financial records; Tax records; Advertising -- Tourism; McClean, Denise; Brooklyn Children's Museum; Brooklyn Museum; Brooklyn Public Library; Prospect Park Zoo (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park Alliance
- Series 1: Administrative Records
  - Sub-series 1.1: Founding Documents
    - 1023 and IRS Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Certificate of Incorporation Filing Receipt, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 501(3)(c) Correspondence, 2002-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Certificate of Incorporation Paperwork, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Tax Exempt Certification, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Charities Registration Form, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - SS-4, 2 August 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - SS-4 Application, 27 Feb 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Name Registration with Department of State, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Incorporation Committee Resolution 4/21/01 Meeting, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Davis Polk and Wardwell, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dun and Bradstreet, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Employee Passport Card, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Embosser with Heart of Brooklyn Seal], circa 2001 (Box 2)
  - Sub-series 1.2: Planning Documents
    - Brooklyn Cultural Consortium Planning, 1997-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    - Business Plan for the Brooklyn Cultural Consortium, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - [Sign Location Planning Map], 1999 (Folder Flat File)
      General
      Map was removed from Brooklyn Cultural Consortium Planning binder in box 1, folders 14-16.
    - Strategic Plan, 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series 1.3: History
    - Heart of Brooklyn History, 2000-2011 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series 1.4: Hard Drive
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    The hard drive in this collection is not available to researchers, file access will be provided on alternative hardware.
    Scope and Contents
    Heart of Brooklyn had no record retention policy. The files that appear in this sub-series are a copy of the organization's server at the time of their closing. The hard drive includes ten top-level folders with documents in the following file formats: .doc, .xls, .pdf, .jpeg, .psd, .ai, .tiff, .mov, .wav, .aup, .m4v, .tmp, .ppt. See below for a non-exhaustive summary of each top-level folder.
    About HOB
    Heart of Brooklyn closing documents, general information about boards, founding documents including certificate of incorporation and a tax exemption letter, a list of organizational accomplishments, business plan, budget, and member return on investment information.
    Closing
    Conference call minutes (2012-2013), financial and budget information, contacts, office equipment inventories, transition checklists, employee separation documents, closing statements. Includes restricted documents.
    Commerical Revitalization
    Certified financial statements (CFS), audits, quarterly reports, neighborhood scoping notes and proposals, budgets, applications, contracts, press, photos, Washington Avenue business inventory, financial statements, Washington Avenue demographic and income profiles, surveys, and Washington Avenue/Prospect Heights Association documents. Includes restricted documents.
    Development
    Audit information for fiscal years 2002-2012, lists of funders, lists of programs, board information, budget information, W-9s, boilerplate documents, evaluations, stats, information about current and possible donors, press releases, and meeting notes.
    Dissolution 501(3)(C)
    Dissolution paperwork filed with New York State and New York City, member articles of incorporation, signed affidavits, documents concerning the transfer of the Heart of Brooklyn archives to the Center for Brooklyn History, member financial statements, bank statements, fiscal year 2013-2022 documents, dissolution timeline, and meeting notes. Includes restricted documents.
    General and Administrative
    2011 annual meeting documents, board information, member trustee information, director meeting agendas and minutes, committee contact lists, financial documents, staff information, photo release forms, staff meeting agendas and notes, hiring and onboarding documents, HOB launch materials, and focus group promotional materials. Includes restricted documents.
    Image Bank
    Photographs include the Heart of Brooklyn 10th anniversary celebration, annual meetings, BCAP, economic development programs, trollies, visitors and events at member institutions, stock images, Brooklyn landmarks, wayfinding, and images for the website and social media.
    IMLS
    Coming Up Taller award documents, grant applications, Building Strong Community Networks documents.
    Programs
    Various government relations documents, social media graphics and analytics, print and digital marketing documents, contracts, agreements, and visitor survey materials. Also included is documents concerning various tourism programs (FAM Tour, Brooklyn Pass) promotional materials, partnerships, budgets, programs, research, itineraries, and reports.
    Documents concerning various economic development programs including budgets, promotional materials, photographs, meeting notes, planning materials, contact lists, and surveys. BCAP camp and afterschool budgets, curriculums, photographs. Heart of Brooklyn Connection promotional materials, schedules, maps, signage, branding, reports, task force meeting notes and minutes. Employee Passport participant list, contracts, photographs, graphics. Jazz Brooklyn Beats promotional materials, budgets, funding information, photographs, meeting notes, and permits. Building Strong Community Networks materials including financials, meeting notes, funding information, research, graphics, reports. Includes restricted documents.
    Support Materials
    Logos, staff biographies, poster and brochure designs, presentations, press releases, style guides, and letterheads.
    Conditions Governing Access
    The following files are restricted due to sensitive personal information:
    Closing-Staff
    Commercial Revitalization - SBS 2013 - AvenueNYC Application - Contractual Paperwork
    Dissolution 5013C - Patterson Belknap Invoices
    General and Administrative - BPL Requested Items - Payroll
    Programs - HOB Connections - Invoices - Thavma's Invoice
    - HOB Server Files (Box 2)
- Series 2: Surveys and Reports
  - Brooklyn Cultural Programming Collaborative, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Prospect Park Zoo Visitor Survey Report, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Institute of Museum and Library Services Reports, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Heart of Brooklyn Visitor Survey: Spring 2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Multi-Site Visitor Survey: Spring 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Building Strong Community Networks: A Position Paper, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - [Heart of Brooklyn Report], 2009 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Building Strong Community Networks, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - A Collaboration Workbook (2011-2013), 2014 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Programs
  - Experience the Heart of Brooklyn, 2004-2007 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Crown Heights Renaissance Draft Plan, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Crown Heights Renaissance 2006-2007, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series 4: Promotional Materials
  - [Brochures], 2004-2011 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - [10th Anniversary Magazine], 2011 (Box 4, Folder 5)